all right so foundation of deep learning
me again all right
yeah so again do interrupt me is going
to be the last class we have in person
we have a very bad situation especially
in Italy
people are dying we don't have any more
beds in the hospitals we don't have
doctors doctor doctors are working like
24/7 and they are going home and they
are effecting their own families so it's
like a really bad situation right now
back home and it looks like we are two
weeks away from that situation under
here so just wash your hands try not to
go in very crowded places stay healthy
okay please a third class
all right self or unsupervised learning
generative models capabilities so here
I'm going to be giving you some eye
candies such that you can get hungry and
then I can feed you with the first part
of this lesson this lesson is gonna be
split in two parts half is gonna be
today hot is gonna be online through
zoom I think system so who hangs up who
thinks the picture on the left it's real
okay now hands up who thinks that the
picture on the right is real okay who
thinks that both of them are real who
think that this one is fake who thinks
that this one is fake who thinks that
both are fake okay you are right so
these two images have been generated by
modeling that we trained actually this
guy Cara's train so if you go on the
website this person does not exist you
can find several examples of very
good-looking non-existent people if you
keep clicking sometimes you're gonna
find some person with a hole in their
faces that's kind of very easy to
recognize that is not quite likely a
real person but otherwise
look pretty legit you can notice that
they have very nice teeth very nice
you know cheek you know chicken feet
like things or you call them you can
clearly tell here though that if you
check on the background behind the
network is not producing a very accurate
the ground although the faces looks very
good why is that
because the network has been provided
many samples and those samples are
refiguring
faces the thing that is not constant is
the background right so that the
background is the variable here and
therefore you can't learn any possible
background so the become the ground will
look like some weird stuff because there
is much more variability then what are
the possible appearances of a face how
many given a face how many in how many
way you can you distort her face a human
face like if your face how many degrees
of freedom does he have ah you know this
answer right we already covered this in
class eight
she said eight how much thousand and
fifty fifty yeah that's 50 correct so
you have roughly fifty a mass of
something less plus you know rotation
tilting and what so not what not so you
know all possible it's just a manifold
in 50 dimensions so everything nice
doesn't quite is outside that manifold
although this picture you know RF
several megapixel pictures so each point
here is living in this huge dimensional
space although all the possible
variations are restrained to a subspace
okay so that's the training manifold the
data manifold okay check out their
website okay so we have here a very cute
dog oh and on the other side less cute
bird sorry oh yeah if you do a linear
interpolation between the dog oh and the
bird what are you expecting to see in
the middle and for this one I'm gonna be
actually turning off the light not
turning it back on the next soon after
so again so a blurry image what do you
mean so what do you expect to get over
here
roughly yeah you can talk back so I'm
gonna be doing 100% DS 1 + 0 90 % D is
on Plus 10 percent 80 percent D is on +
20 % this one so what are you gonna be
seen here you should guess you're less
than usual so you actually have to talk
back more than usual
flying square no ok so you have a dog
you have a bird if I do like a linear
interpolation of these two images in
pixel space what do you get second sorry
yeah super super position right so
you're gonna get something that looks
like this you can get basically overlay
of the first image with a second image
alright so let's get back here and
instead let's do a interpolation in the
latent space of the network so I input
both those two guys I get a 2 and
representation those hidden layers then
I do a linear interpolation between the
hidden layers and then I do the decoding
part what do you expect to see here and
you still have to talk back to me you
have to shout the background feel a mess
but then what's gonna be this the
subject right right so you're gonna be
starting scene where the dog and then a
doggie bird okay and that's how it looks
birdie dog in a birdie birdie birdie dog
in a doggie bird okay
alright this is a network that did this
atrocious Frankie's blasphemy
you should watch full make a full metal
alchemist episode where the father takes
the daughter and the dog and makes
something similar it was so interesting
ok if you watch cartoons Brotherhood
right a second second season okay
aha
I don't know because it's a lot of green
so I guess it got rid of it I don't know
and I guess it yeah I don't know
good question though yeah good I so let
me show you a few more so this stuff
comes from
Brock's article and that you can you
have a smaller like so the first one you
have a small version of those images we
start from something like looks like a
shark or a monta I think is a name then
that stuff looks like a poly puss or how
do you call them again octopus right no
yeah it's something like octopus and
then the octopus becomes like monkey and
then it looks like a dog right so you
can see the shark becomes octopus that
becomes a monkey that becomes a dog so
interesting like how you can change
breeds by just having the final two
points fixed and then you walk through
the latent space so you have another one
here you go from these puppy here to our
bird so again you have a birdie squirrel
whatever and then you have a bird and
then the other side you have a doggie or
this one you have like the dismally guy
what's called a chunk skunk thank you
oh oh that's why you smell like a skunk
is the same right huh okay I see so that
if you have a skunk here and then you
get to a dog rabbit it actually looks a
lot of a dog after this thing here and
finally you get a bird turn into a fly I
think these are pretty awesome examples
so this should make you hungry such that
I can feed you with the second part of
the class right so you have this image
of one side you have this image on the
other side you get the embeddings and
you do some basically interpolation of
the embedding you can check out the
paper for more details the point here is
just to show you that the difference
between interpolation in pixel space
yeah what is the difference between
interpolation in pixel space in the
latent space so the latent space capture
what is the basic
semantics of an image and therefore you
you go from the pixel space which kind
of doesn't really play well with our
tools to kind of more well-behaved space
which is our internal hidden
representation of the data of the end of
the network again this is just to give
you some appetite right not I'm not
gonna be I'm not form a little what next
okay you can zoom on dogs you can shift
you can shift on the X on the Y you can
do change the brightness the interesting
part here is that when you change the
brightness actually you change day to
day to night or night today because
that's what the most normal brightness
change in pictures looks like okay so
whenever you change brightness you
actually change the time of the day or
you have a 2d rotation or even a 3d
rotation is so interesting means that
the network and somehow have a internal
representation of the 3d world
that's something yan was mentioning
yesterday if you shift you know a little
bit you see this kind of parallax then
the easiest way to express to basically
address this you know phenomenon is
actually to imply that there is a 3d war
okay so in this case they trained the
network in order to actually be able to
you know handle specific transformation
actually I have to put the reference on
this paper again I'm just giving you
some how to say I can this okay I'm not
giving you any more any formal thing
right now in this case actually I like
this on so much you can get the animal
version of your picture right so you
could try to stop by don't try with
hentai right we don't want to do those
things okay all right so some of you
actually know this stuff interesting
thank you
right the one that don't it's okay just
forget all right okay this is other
stuff which is pretty cool like you can
go from low resolution to high
resolution from the left hand side to
hide right hand side and here you have a
few examples but this is of course it's
black on white it's much easier to do
this stuff and the same for the zebra
and this is a pre deep learning
technique so they were just using some
hierarchical model nevertheless it works
pretty well and then a few years later
you've actually gave Garcia getting you
you know really high this is like the
hub sampling by doing like linear
interpolation by linear interpolation
and instead this one is gonna be the up
sampling down with the neural net and
the final one is actually the real image
you can see clearly on the third row how
these Asian dude became European white
that bias right correct so the network
has seen a lot of white dudes and
therefore the most the easiest way to
reconstruct a kind of unknown face
features it can be to plug there a white
dude face or this lady looks like she
has in she's having a stroke because she
we don't have many side views of these
images right these this lady became a
changed sex on the bottom side and then
this guy it looks like he had an
accident because again we didn't have
many glasses on the dataset therefore
the network you know so some very dark
thing and then you know implied someone
just punched him very hardly okay but
again this is very old stuff I mean we
are four years in the future now again
these are the first results and this
allows you to leverage you know actual
data in order to fill in the gaps and
the gaps are what are they actually
actual detail we have very very many new
results recently but these organ are the
kind of pioneering result and pioneering
examples one more here you basically
block the face with a gray square and
then you ask the network to reconstruct
the face such that it gives you
the best-looking closing point right so
you take an image which is staying on
the training manifold you put a patch on
the face this patch will make the image
go away from the training manifold now
you can do for example gradient descent
in this energy space such that you can
find what is the closest point like the
point with the lowest energy that is
associated to that specific initial
image okay so you get an image you
perturb the image you that makes it go
away from the training manifold and then
you can do great in the saint's in the
energy landscape such that you can pick
the whatever sample looks like the most
you know it's only the closest sample on
the training manifold and this is some
stuff yan was covering yesterday about
energy based model whenever you learn an
energy then you can actually use the
energy to do inference to do inference
you actually have to minimize the energy
right so energy minimization means
inference not training training
something else
again we're going to be covering more
detail energy based models in the
following classes here you have another
few examples one using a variational
encoder and another using generative
other cyanate this is also another
example from Reed this is crazy you can
go from English description to actual
drawing of what the English description
mean right so you go from a sequence I
guess to a vector which is like the
concept and then from the concept you
use a decoder so it's a generative net
which is going to be decoding your
specific output and that was pretty much
it for the eye candy so this should make
you very hungry for the second part of
the class are you hungry
yeah I didn't have dinner either either
okay all right so out encoders
what are these stuff I'm supervised
learning so this is our first model
we're going to be diving into in order
to see how we can train a network
without targets or labels what are
target's what was the difference between
target and labels
you already know everything someone else
prediction means both of them are
actually given both of them are
annotations thank you so labels are
going to be categorical you can label
things this is a chair that's a table
that doors targets are going to be you
know the target okay all right so we're
going to be observing how we can train
this model without actually having
targets or labels so this is the first
network which is the architecture we are
going to be playing with it's very
similar to what we observe so far but
the big difference is that we start from
the bottom we know already why it's pink
you got to intermediate hidden layer in
green then you get top two the input so
the output of the network is going to be
the prediction of the input okay so you
have also a different kind of
representation you may have so that
those are DEA questions the hidden
layers going to be the rotation squash
rotation on my input and then the final
output is going to be the I guess squash
version of the rotation of the hidden
okay where rotation means affine
transformations we have some
dimensionality so we shoot towards D but
then both X and X hat live in the RN
therefore the second part is going to be
our generative Network this one that
goes from h2x hots is going to be my
generative net and here you have a
different diagram which is basically
doing the same thing but this one is you
know some people prefer these diagrams
where the actual transformations are
made in boxes okay so you have people
saying this is a two layer neural net
although we know that is a how many
layer neural net how many balls you see
three layers neural network fantastic
that our my convention okay if we use
yawns notation then we also have okay
hold on so you actually can have some
tights weights in order to be trying to
reproduce somehow piece
although you don't have guarantees over
the order of the different weight all of
the different basis but if we use the
onion notation we are going to be also
adding those kind of little project is
there which are representing the
transformations okay so why are we using
out encoders what's the point of
predicting my input let's say I use a
identity matrix okay I provide input
which is a vector
I put apply this vector I do want my
identity matrix times my vector I get
the same vector this out encoder so you
get the same thing as you put in why the
hell are we doing this so you don't have
the input when you predict but then I
can just learn the identity matrix right
I have identity matrix I put some
thinning I get something out I put
something in I put something out I get
put same thing in I get the same thing
out so the most thing the most trivial
thing to learn for a network would be
the identity matrix right I thing I put
inside comes out and that's how we train
this stuff second sorry if d is
less right okay there is a first point
so if we have a weapon if you have
intermediate dimensionality D lower than
n therefore we can start seeing what
this guy this stuff can be used for for
example could be used for compression so
if I have an intermediate representation
which takes less space than my input
representation I can use this encoder is
a compressor then I have my hinny
representation my code which is you know
addressing what specific input is it
takes to this space so I can use a you
know image compressor for example for
example here so that was my initial idea
for out encoders but that's just one
type of
and it's kind of you know not the proper
way of thinking about these guys
so another encoder task is to be able to
reconstruct data that lives on the
manifold okay so we have a data manifold
we get some points we have data points I
use these points for training my system
and I'd like my out encoder to be able
to reconstruct only things that live on
the training manifold on the data
manifold okay so that's our that's
actually what the task what is the task
of these out encoders only to
reconstruct a small subset and I getting
tripped off by my microphone one sec I
only we should okay this is too short
okay we should be only able to
reconstruct we had to enforce only to be
able to reconstruct a small set of
possible inputs okay now it becomes
interesting because if you can only
reconstruct a small set of inputs then
you cannot reconstruct things that are
away right so for example like before I
show you I have put I put a picture I
have a picture and I have a gray box in
front of my face so I take my point and
I take it away from my training manifold
if I try to reconstruct it and I network
and only reconstruct things that are on
a manifold it will reconstruct something
that is here which doesn't have that
patch on the face okay you see this or
no so if you're only constrained to
reconstruct things that have been
observed during training any variation
that you apply to the you know new
inputs later on during when you can be
using this network is going to be read
removed because the network will be
insensitive to that kind of
perturbations so let's see a bit of more
details about this stuff is it clear so
far
yes no okay all right so let's figure
out what our D reconstruction losses we
have we can use so the first one we have
the classical you know loss for the
overall data set is going to be the
average between my per sample losses
okay and so there are two person
Nasus the first person per loss is going
to be the binary binary cross-entropy
which is going to be penalizing a lot if
you make a mistake
so the output the the targets are going
to be 0 or 1 so I have a categorical
distribution and then your input does
not be sorry you're out who's going to
be something that also leaves between 0
and 1 so you have a sigmoid network a
sigmoid a nonlinear function at the end
and then you get you try to minimize
this guy here otherwise if you have real
value inputs and outputs which are for
example images color images you may want
to use the MSC okay all right so as
someone yeah it's the your friend
they're mentioned before we have you
know pretty it's pretty obvious obvious
to think about like under complete
hidden layer a hundred complete hidden
layer has a dimensionality which is
smaller than the size of the input so in
this case the network not perhaps copy
or use the identity matrix because you
have an intermediate representation
which is smaller and then you had to
expand this one back to the original
dimensionality again you can use a under
complete hidden layer how to encoder for
doing compression for example ok so this
is pretty standard I would say does it
make sense so far ok so we're gonna play
with this in a second on the notebook
nevertheless I will say I actually like
this one more and you are gonna be
telling me why you should be able to I
mean you should have all the ingredients
it's gonna be what's this is the six
week I think seventh six
six week seventh week I think I'm not
sure why do I want a larger intermediate
representation
[Music]
right so we always said that the larger
we go into intermediate presentation the
easiest is going to be the optimization
right and so although the information
that is contained in the first layer and
in the hidden layer is gonna be the same
I can't add information but it's much
easier now for the network to play with
a representation that has you know much
many more dimensions the point is that
we can simply learn now the identity
matrix and we're going to be just
copying everything you know you copy the
first guy in the first post post spot
the second guy you copy here the third
one you copied here now you copy
everything through you haven't learned
nothing have learned the identity
therefore we have to learn we have to
apply some other types of constraint for
the information and so we have to learn
how to introduce now we have to
introduce now a information bottleneck
okay although we enlarge the
intermediate representation we have to
constrain the representation we have to
constrain the possible configurations
that the hidden layer can take the input
layer can take as many configurations as
you want the hidden layer should be only
containing we represent the possible
configuration that the training data are
the data on that manifold can have okay
so the input can be everything you want
but you can be training only with data
that is on the manifold therefore the
hidden layer
only to be able to model to capture what
is develop ility within the training
data and be insensitive to anything that
is outside
okay such that we can have a selective
reconstruction of a subset of this in
very large input space are you with me
is no unless we are done see now how we
avoid overfitting on the training data
so a few there are a few ways to do this
make this stuff on the right-hand side
work and moreover you may want to have
you can have the same rationale also for
this less than side guy here so let's
say I have a super awesome decoder then
my encoder should could simply put all
my training data as you know first
training data is first point second
training data is gonna be number two
third training data same poles gonna be
number three so I can associate each of
my training data is one number one two
three four five six seven whatever and
now you have the decoder has memorized
all the training data points and then
you just output the training point that
you want from this kind of selector
right so you potentially may only need
only one ball here one only one neuron
in the hidden layer in order to have a
network that does overheat as long as
the decoder in the encoder are very
powerful
okay so the point is your colleague
mentioned yeah how do we avoid
overfitting this stuff can over fit to
this stuff will over fit unless we are
you know I'm kind of you know careful
about how we design these things so
there are a few different methods there
are contrastive methods in there are
there are regular ice metals and there
are architectural methods we have seen
yesterday as well something we can be
quarry now a few of these and we have 20
minutes left okay yeah
next slide
yeah so do you know is an alt encoder
how does it work I take my input the
pink one I put it away from my original
point so these are my training this is
my data manifold each of these points
are gonna be you know samples are gonna
be providing for the training I take my
point and I displace it okay how I just
add random crap okay cool
now I didn't force the network to be
reconstructing that initial point right
so this is the denoising auto-encoder
you take a point from your training
manifold you take it you move it away
and then you enforce the network to take
it back here I take the same point I
take it away on the other direction and
then I put it back here I take the same
point I put it another direction and I
put it down here okay so what are we
learning right now we will be learning a
vector field which has everything coming
back to this point then I start moving
around my training manifold and I have
all this kind of vector field like the
vector field is gonna be all pointing
towards the training sample right but if
you have a training sample here and a
training sample here this guy will try
to attract here these on tire tracks
there so things that are on a manifold
stay there things were outside manifold
will be you know collapsing towards the
manifold okay questions okay all right
so actually there is a caveat caveat or
a caveat caveat let me say Kavya
thank you all right we assume that we
are injecting the same noise
distribution we are going to observe in
reality in this way we can learn how
vastly recover from it right so if we
assume that we have access to the type
of cultivation we are going to be
observing
Ronit inference then we can train the
model to be insensitive deluded to those
kind of perturbations and this is a very
big if okay
therefore oh nice pictures okay all
right so this is my training data this
is my data pink points and I'm gonna be
turning off the lights so I have here my
pink points which look white to you then
I have the orange points with our which
are the displaced points against so they
are originated from these points here
and then I displace them in any very
dark mini directions then I train my
network to get all these orange points
back to original starting point right
and so this is the output of the network
I input this cloud of orange points in
the network I trained my network to
output the points on the actual spiral
and therefore these are the blue points
are going to be my reconstructions of
the network okay so if points were
already on the manifold they didn't move
in points are far away from the manifold
they moved a lot guess what I can
measure how much they moved and that's
gonna be your energy how cool is this
huh okay maybe you haven't understood
yet so in this case in order to be a bit
more thorough I just send every possible
XY combination on this plane inside my
network right so here you have this line
because because all these bottom left
corner got squashed down here and now
you can see here points are quite sparse
and then there are very very many of
them densely occupying manifold
nevertheless there are a few points here
right and so this is showing you with
colors what is the distance those points
have traveled so points over here in the
bottom left corner have traveled one
unit and they got down here I think
points over here and travel also like
0.9 something and they went down here as
you can tell points within these two
branches didn't go anywhere yeah why is
that
tracked by both points on this side and
both on this side you know on average
during training nevertheless if you
forget about you know having stuff that
is curling on its own you have
everything just drops down to here guess
what I can put the points that have just
moved a little bit again inside the out
encoder and I can keep doing this a few
times until these points collapse down
to the manifold okay all right
or I can do something good I'm cool that
is a trick right so what did I do here
this is my denoising auto-encoder where
I get to the initial point where did I
where I start from my displacement from
right so I got my initial point I
displaced and then they forced the
network to go back to the initial point
what happened here how did I fix this
how can you fix this Ridge here and this
black this dark region any guess you can
send them randomly or hold on someone
their top right push it up how do I push
it out oh okay pushing up would be also
very good
so I also try to push up everything that
is not on the manifold didn't quite work
what did I do here it's a very is a hack
okay it's not elegant it cannot be done
in a high dimensional space so what I've
done here is gonna be make your point
fall on the closest point on a manifold
it so I did an exhaustive search of the
closest point on the manifold and then I
enforce my network to always make my
points fall on the closest point
although they were may be generated from
another initial point right so if this
point over here initially originated
from here but it's gonna be always
falling down on this direction just a
few points will not be you know they are
just in there in the middle way and they
don't fall anywhere all right so
now in more dimensions everything is
Farah right so it doesn't quite work we
haven't covered that not work yet okay
and I show you next time I guess well
next next next time yeah so in this case
I've done the denoising auto-encoder in
this case I got the displace point to
fall on to the closest point on a
manifold so I did an exhaustive search
it's it's simple because I have hundred
and fifty points here but it's a hack
you cannot do that in reality anyhow the
point is that we kind of have developed
somehow kind of understanding and this
one instead that the unruly likes but I
am not yet able to make it work
so I guess I'm not that smart yet it's
regularized out encoder in this case I
have a l1 regularization term cost on my
hidden representation so I force my
network to come up with hidden
representations which are short and they
are like short of a few dimensions right
so if I have a one regularization of my
hidden representation I will only have a
few items active at a given time the
problem is that if you set all those
other elements to zero and then you have
zero gradients to send back okay and so
then you may want to use target prop and
other cute fancy things and I still am
working on this so I have no idea how to
make it work the point is that this is
the regularization term so this is the
l1 penalty on the hidden representation
and this black dark here the region
should be actually extending all around
again it's very hard for the moment for
me to get this to work not saying that
is impossible and just saying that I'm
not smart enough all right contract the
out encoder and then we going to be seen
the not works let me turn on the lights
such that or maybe not I don't know
shall I I like it so much dark okay
whatever
okay back on the camera right again data
manifold points training points what is
VI a contract adult encoder doing so
this guy here it simply have the
reconstruction term plus that thing here
what is it
gradient of my hidden representation
with respect to the input norm square in
the overall loss right
so my overall loss will try to minimize
the variation of my hidden layer given
variations on the input okay so here you
want to have a representation for the
input which is not changing that much is
I wiggled my input and so this one
basically makes makes you insensitive to
what makes you sorry insensitive to
reconstruction of analyzing sensitivity
to the reconstruction directions so you
actually will be able to reconstruct
things over the manifold but it will
make you otherwise insensitive to any
other possible direction and so this one
we don't have an assumption over the
perturbation I'm applying adjust
insensitive to everything but then I
still have many points here so you will
have to minimize the reconstruction as i
provide different samples okay and you
penalize incentivize as well and that's
just penalized finally okay ten minutes
left
finally what does this out in color tone
as you can see I can use matplotlib very
well here we have this training manifold
which is my single dimensional you know
thing going in three dimensions and here
I have all those data points okay cool
so the X lives on this set of data and
it lives in RN what an out encoder has
to do is going to be basically
getting that curly line stretched down
in one direction right and therefore you
have there your Z in this case is called
latent space and so you get the first
one there and then the second one over
there the point is that how do I know
how can I go from these back to here I
know if I'm in this first location I can
go back to this location I know if I'm
in this location I can go back there I'm
not entirely sure what's happening here
there is no I only have training samples
right so I only have the correspondence
between points in the input space and
points on the latent space I don't have
any correspondence between regions of
the input space and regions of the
latent space okay so as as of right now
you only know how to connect input to
regions here in the latent space and how
to get back then we have learned that
the denoising auto-encoder takes the
input shakes it but you enforced to go
back here
same point and then you go back to the
other location to define a location
right so you take this one you shake it
it's gonna be always going here and then
you'll get back to the correct location
or the Dino is in the contractive you're
going to be the input and every you try
to penalize any possible wiggling of
this one when you wiggle this okay this
is contractive out encoder nevertheless
how can I start from here move around
and get something that actually looks
like a decent output meaning if I
translate this one if I have a dog here
and a bird here the embedding speedy
latent space if I move on this line
how can I assure that the things on this
line here will actually look like
meaningful transformations in here we
don't know that right now we only know
that this image is connected to this
point this image is connected to this
point we don't have any knowledge about
what kind of behavior how well we have
the space is whenever I move
in this space convert to down here right
so we don't know how this decoder that
goes from the latent space to the input
space is behaving when we are not
exactly in the points right so right now
we have points mapping all day next time
we're gonna watching we're going to be
learning how to map regions of the input
space with regions of the hidden space
okay right now we have a point point all
right so not books in the last seven
minutes thank you for sticking with me
yeah I'm moving too much and I'm
painting they work it PDL Jupiter Conda
Conda the faith PDA Jupiter not pocus
okay so I'm gonna be using this out
encoder just the number ten okay over
there it's invisible I know but it's
gonna be number ten all right so I'm
gonna be just executing stuff through
okay all right so what are we doing here
let me see we import some random crap
can you see right yeah you can complain
if you don't see things right I can't
check too many things so we import some
stuff we have an image conversion
routine which is simply adding adding
one and then multiplying by zero half
because I have otherwise my data when I
get my data I try to get it to zero mean
and I have also in a range that is
between minus 0.5 to plus 5 so it is
centered then here to get it back by
someone so instead of being 0 meaning go
0.5 mean and then I actually have so it
goes from my it starts from minus 1 to
plus 1 then here I just someone so it
goes from 0 to 2 and then I get it 0
- one this is a some display in routines
and here okay I show you that I subtract
0.5 and I divide by 0.5 my data those
are the em nice digits from me on
website here we set the device if you
want to run on CP on GPU and in this
case we have images that are the digit
we saw that when we were training the
convolutional net which are 28 by 28
pixels and in this case I'm going to be
creating a note encoder which has a 30
dimensional intermediate layer right
hidden layer so we go from 784 to 30 and
time and then back to 784 so here is
gonna be my out encoder model just a
linear layer affine transformation like
228 square 2d hyperbolic tangent and
then I have the decoder which is my
generative model which goes from the
hidden space the latent space which is D
228 square and then I have again
hyperbolic tangent such that I limit my
output range to minus one to plus one
and my forward simply is gonna be send
things through the encoder and decoder I
created my model and then I create my
criterion which is gonna be the MSC loss
learning rate and atom optimizer and so
this is gonna be the training part so
you're gonna be having whatever 20
evokes the first part is going to be
sending the images through the model
this number one right number two is
going to be computation of the loss
which is line number 15 then third point
is going to be clearing the gradient
otherwise we accumulate so that's number
17 then we do back propagation
computation of the partial derivative or
the final loss with respect to the
weights that is number 18 and finally we
do a step backwards in the direction of
the easy depth direction of the gradient
you step backward I'm talking a lot
because the computer is just training ok
all right so you can see here we went
through 20 books and actually let me
okay let me show you how they look so
these are the reconstruction of my
network okay these are the output of the
network given that we compress them -
that's 30 dimensional intermediate
representation I'm gonna show you the
currents in a sec let me change this one
to a denoising auto-encoder so here I
create a drop out module which is
randomly turning off neurons
I create my nose mask noise mask and
then I create my dead images which are
multiplying those images to this binary
mask and then I send to the network
those bad images these I traded images
and I train this stuff again we also
like to get to 500 dimensions right so
it is owner complete hidden layer and
then we train again okay this is correct
and this is training okay all right so
just recap of what's the difference
between the previous training at the
current training alright so we were
saying that before we were just using a
under complete out encoder so we were
going from 784 dimensional is input to a
30 dimensional hidden layer but now we
are going to be using a over complete
still I use 500 here which is less than
a semi 784 so one proper question would
be why are 500 dimensions like why it
does a elting color with 500 Meg
dimensional hidden layer is consider or
can be considered over complete think
about the number of pixels that are
black for example on average in these
images alright so we actually already
run this part so we were down to the
training how does the training changes
right now I have a dropout mask here
which is allowing me to introduce some
kind of perturbation on the original
images then I have my noise which is
simply applying a drop of mask on a
vector of
is this going to be useful for later
visualizations then I create my images
bed the perturbed images which are
simply the multiplication of my image
times this noise so if we didn't have
any neuron dropped the noise would be
just those ones and that you get 1 times
image so you got the same image
otherwise when the neurons are dropping
set to 0 the image now is going to be
multiplied by 0 for no specific values
of the pixels so this image bed our
images with black dot then I input
inside my model this image pad ok and
then the criterion it's between like is
the distance between the output and the
original image man so before we were
like in here we are inputting these
perturbed images inside the model so
those are points that are outside the
training manifold but then I enforce
them to be the original point right so
you get the original point you perturb
it so you put it away and then you
enforce the network to actually I'll put
this on so it's going to be trying to
contrast any kind of perturbation that
happened to this original point ok all
right the rest is the same rank 0 guard
backwardness step so this is also train
and we can check how this reconstruction
look and if I can remember from the
previous iteration they look much more
actually clean because I guess we are
using a much larger hidden layer right
but before we couldn't use such a large
hidden layer because you would have been
overfitting right if you try to
reconstruct things that are always in
the same point we just can copy them
over in this case you can't copyright
because the input is not this point but
the input is actually the displace point
right so you learn a vector field that
is bringing you back to the original
position on the training manifold ok so
let's go down and let's visualize the
actually let's have a look to the
previous filters I didn't show you so
these are the filters of the outer
corner with a under complete hidden
layer ok and so you can see here there
are some
of patterns in this central area of
these filters so these are the filters
which are simply my rows of my W metrics
that have been reshaped in a basically
no image such that I can visualize
formula so in this case in this notebook
we are not using any convolutional
network
we are just using those images that have
been enrolled in protectors and they are
compared there and you know multiply it
like scalar product against the DD
vectors right of the of my matrix so
these are the rows of my matrix that
have been reshaped such that you can
make sense of what they represent so
here for example it looks like there is
like a loop upper loop detector or not a
detector because there are purple right
so these are would be negative the
output here you have like a C rule here
looks like some eight over three and
then you have this kind of right this
this this kernel over here and that has
basically learned nothing or well that's
the only one that didn't learn much
moreover you can notice that all those
points outside the region where the
number happened or any kind of
interesting thing happened all these
points are multiplied by a constant
right because it's outside a digit and
so things don't change there and
therefore these noisy kernels over there
you know the on average they will
produce a score of zero right and
therefore you're gonna have that the
network didn't care about giving any
specific value to these outstanding
without out there other points outer
pictures because I can on average they
will not contribute to the final score
what happened now when we are inputting
the data which have a variable amount of
like pixel set to zero now these points
will in matter right because it's not
longer continuous the value of the image
and so if I show you the new kernels
um how cool is this right this is
completely different
can you remember so here you can still
have some pattern right but then in the
majority of these kernels regardless
like if you don't consider the one that
did not did not learn anything so this
colonel here are didn't learn much but
all the other kernels that I have have
learned some kind of specific edge
filter or shape specific features
you know shape filter all the outside
pixels have now been set to some zero
value I think of some somebody that is
uniform right because again the input
images now are no longer constant in the
areas outside digit and therefore the
value of the pixels well the value of
the of the value of the kernel thing
though specifically specific regions now
do matter this is a big big difference
and again this this this maps here this
courier didn't learn anything okay so
let's now compare our denoising
auto-encoder we've failed
state-of-the-art algorithms for
denoising images so here we're going to
be importing some functions from the
opencv library there is the neighbor
strokes and then the tele algorithm so
it's imported and let's see how this
stuff look so here the first image is
the noise image the one we generated
before these are the maps of own ones
where we have dropped out some specific
values to set to 0 right so yellow is
one and purple is 0 in this case then
the second part is going to be the bed
images so these are the bed images
meaning purple is minus 1 yellow is plus
1 and then this green is the zero value
so all those black points like purple
points in the first row are here
represented in in green so those are the
values that are being set to 0 there are
mask value then we have the original
images and the reconstructions from our
you know is it not encoder which broke
reasonably okay if you think that half
of the pixels were actually nice right
so these are like half of the pixels are
provided to the network and then the
network actually reconstructed
both net and what look like the original
image more or less right cool Quan
so let's now have a look to what
the set of the art algorithms output are
so we can start with the Thalia and then
their strokes and so this is Thalia and
this is never stroke right so as you can
tell here the quality of our modern is
clearly a superior in terms of you know
qualitative qualitative output
nevertheless pay attention that this
modern works just for this kind of
specific perturbation that we have
introduced and then we haven't learned
how to counteract okay so again he note
encoder that we have trained in a in a
minute performs much better than
state-of-the-art computer vision
algorithms again when the ADA is
available okay and so I think that's it
for today thank you for listening
subscribe to my channel the non de
notification bed if you'd like to have
information about latest videos and
follow me on Twitter peace